A Finding Aid to the Jacqueline Skiles Papers, 1963-1980, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Jacqueline Skiles papers
1963-1980
Archives of American Art
Skiles, Jacqueline Dean, 1937-
AAA.skiljacq
Archival Resource Key
0.7 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor, video artist, printmaker, and educator Jacqueline Skiles measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1963 to 1980. The papers comment on Skiles's feminist activism and career as an educator and exhibiting artist. Found are biographical materials, correspondence, two photographs, printed material, professional files, and writings.
Biographical / Historical
Jacqueline Skiles (1937- ) is a sculptor, printmaker, video artist, educator, and writer in New York City, New York. She has been active in New York feminist arts organizations and co-founded the Women's Interart Center.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Scope and Contents
The papers of sculptor, videotape artist, and educator Jacqueline Skiles measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1963 to 1980. The papers comment on Skiles's feminist activism and career as an educator and exhibiting artist. Found are biographical materials, correspondence, two photographs, printed material, professional files, and writings.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated 1979 by Jacqueline Skiles.
Related Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds an oral history interview of Jacqueline Skiles conducted by Doloris Holmes in 1971 for the Archives of American Art "Art World in Turmoil" oral history project, and the Women's Interart Center records, 1970-1981.
Women artists; Feminism and art; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Printmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Video artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Women sculptors; Women printmakers; Educators -- New York (State) -- New York; Women educators
- Jacqueline Skiles Papers, 1963-1980; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 3
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials include an autobiographical sketch and resumes, ID cards, examples of printed materials designed by Skiles, and an ink drawing. Correspondence is with colleagues, friends, and family, including scattered letters from her parents and husband. Of note is correspondence with Arlene Raven about the Feminist Program at California Institute of the Arts and letters regarding the organization of a protest called "The Stars and Stripes Threaten the Peace." Two photographs depict Skiles at Syracuse University and the Creative Women's Collective, and are taken by L. E. Irvine and Barbara Williams, respectively. Printed materials include gathered material by Skiles regarding affirmative action and sexual discrimination as well as clippings and exhibition material concerning Skiles's career.
  Professional files are found for some of Skiles's professional positions as an educator as well as for her work as an activist. Files may include administrative information, correspondence, notes, and printed material. Of note are papers relating to a discrimination complaint filed by Skiles against Ramapo College, New Jersey. General writings and notes are by Skiles and often concern feminism and the art world. Some writings may have been published in Art Worker's News.
  - Biographical Material, 1963-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Material, Oversized, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Photographs, 1974-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Printed Material, 1971-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - Printed Material, Oversized, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3, Folder 2)
  - Professional Files, Art Worker's News, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Professional Files, Creative Women's Collective, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Professional Files, Ramapo College, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Professional Files, Teaching Files, 1973-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Professional Files, Visiting Video Artist Grant, Syracuse University, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Writings and Notes, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)